Benajah Harvey Carroll papers, Inclusive: 1875-1939, undated, Bulk: 1875-1913, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Benajah Harvey Carroll papers
Inclusive: 1875-1939, undated, Bulk: 1875-1913, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
89
Carroll, Benajah Harvey, 1843 - 1914
6 document boxes.
The Benajah Harvey Carroll papers consist of documents related to the life of Benajah Harvey Carroll. The papers include correspondence, financial records, and literary productions regarding the various positions Carroll held throughout his life.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Benajah Harvey Carroll was born 1843 December 27. He attended Baylor University at Independence until 1861, the beginning of the American Civil War, when he left school to enlist in the Texas Rangers. He later joined the 17th Texas Infantry of the Confederate Army where he served until he was wounded in 1864. A self-identifying skeptic, in 1865 Carroll was converted to Christianity after attending a Methodist Camp meeting. He was ordained as a Baptist minister the next year.
Carroll married his first wife, Ellen Virginia Bell, in 1866. The two had nine children together. After a
short time preaching in small churches throughout central Texas, Carroll was called to become pastor of the First Baptist Church in Waco in 1870. He served there for almost thirty years, until he resigned to become secretary of the Texas Baptist Education Commission in 1899. During his time as pastor, he was instrumental in unifying Texas Baptists under the Baptist General Convention of Texas. Much of the correspondence contained in these papers is related to Carroll’s role as a leader among Texas Baptists.
Also during his tenure at First Baptist Church in Waco, Carroll served for fifteen years on the board of trustees for Baylor University. Often a magnet for controversy, as chairman of the board Carroll was at the center of the transition of Rufus Burleson from acting President of Baylor to President Emeritus in 1897. These papers contain many letters to and from Carroll debating the Burleson controversy.
During his time in Waco, Carroll also served as a professor, teaching Bible and theology classes. He was well respected by his students and had a reputation as an accomplished lecturer. Many of his lectures were transcribed and kept, allowing a rich insight into his classroom. Numerous notebooks containing class notes and exams written by Carroll’s students while attending his class are included in these papers.
After the death of his first wife, Carroll married Hallie Harrison in 1899. The marriage produced one child. Between 1889 and 1906, Carroll led a fundraising campaign to reduce Baylor’s debt. These papers contain correspondence relating to these fundraising campaigns. In 1905, Carroll founded Baylor Theological Seminary, which later moved to Fort Worth and became Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary. He served as its president until his death.
Scope and Content
The Benajah Harvey Carroll papers consist of documents related to the life of Benajah Harvey Carroll. Carroll was the pastor of First Baptist Church in Waco, chairman of the board of trustees of Baylor University, a professor at Baylor, secretary of the Texas Baptist Education Commission, and he founded Baylor Theological Seminary in 1905. Baylor Theological Seminary became Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary and Carroll served as its president until his death on 1914 November 11. The papers include correspondence, financial records and literary productions regarding the various positions Carroll held throughout his life.
Arrangement
The Benajah Harvey Carroll papers, 1875-1939, undated, are arranged in 3 series: I. Correspondence, II. Financial Records, and III. Literary Productions
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 89.
Related Resources
Related references
Benajah Harvey Carroll, (1843-1914).” The Reformed Reader, 1998.
Carroll, J. M, and J. W Crowder. Dr. B.H. Carroll, The Colossus of Baptist History: Pastor, First Baptist Church, Waco, Texas and First President of S.W.B.T. Seminary, Fort Worth, Texas. Fort Worth, Tex.: Crowder, 1946.
J.B. Cranfill. “Life Sketch of B.H. Carroll.” Baptist History Homepage, 1908. Accessed 2020 April 9.
Jonas, Glenn, Rosalie Beck, Charles Deweese, and Mike Williams. “100 Years After the Whitsitt Controversy: The Role of B H Carroll.” Baptist History and Heritage 33, no. 3 (1998 August): 49-56.
Dawson, Joseph Martin. “The Giant Carroll Brothers.” Baptist Standard, 1956 December 29.
Ray, Jeff. D. B.H. Carroll. Nashville, Tenn.: Sunday School Board of the Southern Baptist Convention, 1927.
Reynold, J.A. “Carroll, Benajah Harvey.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2020 April 9.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Carroll, B.H. (Benajah Harvey), 1843-1914.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.; Southern Baptist Convention -- Texas -- Clergy -- Biography.; Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary -- History.
Subjects
Baptists -- Texas.; Baptists -- United States -- Clergy -- Biography.; Waco (Tex.) -- Church history.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Lectures.; Notes (documents); Sermons.
- Correspondence, 1875-1930, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Series includes Benajah Harvey Carroll’s correspondence about Baylor, Southwestern Theological Seminary, and First Baptist Church of Waco. It also includes three letters regarding the Clements Family. Two Clements’ daughters were pupils of Carroll. This series is in average to excellent condition.
  - General, 1875-1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 1892-1893 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1894-1896 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General, 1878-1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General, 1898-1910 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General (1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Regarding the Clements Family, 1914-1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Financial Records, 1895-1896; 2
  This series includes expense reports and financial ledgers and it is in good condition.
  - Reports and Ledger, 1895-1896, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Literary Productions, 1875-1939, undated; 3
  This series is the largest of the Benajah Harvey Carroll Papers. Included are numerous sermons and lectures given by Carroll during his appointments at First Baptist Church of Waco, Baylor University, and Southwestern Theological Seminary. Also included is a collection of class notes taken by three different students in Carroll’s classes. This series is in average to good condition.
  - Tracts, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Addresses, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sermons, 1876-1877 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sermons, 1884-1893 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sermons, 1900-1903 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lectures, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lectures: (1 of 3), 1913 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lectures: (2 of 3), 1913 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Lectures: (3 of 3), 1913 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lectures, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Lectures, 1909 November 10-31 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lectures, 1909 December 1-20 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lectures, 1910 January 3-31 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lectures, 1910 February 2-16 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lectures, 1910 February 17-28 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lectures, 1910 March 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lectures, 1910 March 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Lectures, 1910 April 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lectures, 1910 April (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Lectures, 1910 May 2-13 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Lectures, 1910, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Lectures, 1912 October 2-8 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Lectures, 1912 October 10-21 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lectures, 1912 October 24-November 18 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lectures, 1912 November 19-29 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Printed Material: Baylor, 1910 May 5, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Printed Material: Assorted, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (1 of 2), 1902 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (2 of 2), 1902 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (1 of 2), 1906 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (2 of 2), 1906 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (1 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (2 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (3 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (4 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (5 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (6 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (7 of 11), undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (8 of 11), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (9 of 11), undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (10 of 11), undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Class Notes: Lydia Clements (11 of 11), undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Class Notes: Eualee Trice, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements, 1903 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements, 1906 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements, 1906-1907 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements (1 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements (2 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements (3 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements (4 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements (5 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements (6 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements (7 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements (8 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements (9 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements (10 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements (11 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Class Notes: Dora Clements (12 of 12), undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Yearbook, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 13)